A Guide to the Olmstead Initiative Records of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 2004-2010
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Olmstead Initiative Records of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 2004-2010
The Library of Virginia
51207
4.9 cubic feet (14 Boxes)
Health and Human Resources, Secretary of
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources on 21 February 2014.
Historical Information
A 1999 decision of the U.S. Supreme Court in Olmstead v. L.C., found that the segregation of persons with disabilities constituted discrimination in violation of Title II of the Americans with Disabilities Act. As prescribed by this decision, compliance required that individuals with disabilities receive services in the most integrated setting appropriate to their needs, so that people with disabilities could become as fully integrated in the community as they chose to be. Following the Supreme Court decision, Governor Mark Warner convened the Virginia Olmstead Task Force in 2002. In their One Community report, this 70 member Task Force laid out a vision of Virginia becoming one community for people with disabilities that included 201 recommendations for individual choice of and access to services and supports; sufficient numbers of qualified providers; safe, available, accessible, and affordable housing and transportation; an opportunity to work; a full continuum of care, from self care through institutional care; and accountability to everyone. Julie Stanley was named director of the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities in 2004.
Governor Warner's Executive Order 61 (2004) provided for the infrastructure and process to continue the work that the Task Force began by creating a four cabinet-member, 18 state agency Community Integration Implementation Team, a 19 member stakeholder Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee, and a Director of the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities. The Community Integration Implementation Team was charged with completing cost out and updates to the 201 recommendations in One Community, the Report of the Olmstead Task Force; working to ensure collaborative efforts to complete and annually update a comprehensive cross-governemental strategic plan designed to ensure continued community integration, and to annually report to the Governor on accomplishments. The Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee was tasked with overseeing the implementation of of the Olmstead v. L.C. decision in Virginia; advising the Community Integration Implementation Team and receiving their reports; and preparing reports making recommendations to the Governor. They were also responsible for monitoring the implementation of state and federal laws concerning community integration of Virginians with disabilities; studying all matters that present barriers or challenges to full community integration; and advising and making recommendations to the Director and Implementation Team and reviewing and advising them on the strategic plan. Executive Order 84 (2005) continued the implementation of the Olmstead Initiative.
Governor Kaine continued the Olmstead initiative with the issuance of Executive Order 2 (2006) and directed the Community Integration Implementation Team to work with stakeholder groups to develop a cross-governmental strategic plan for community integration, with input from the Community Integration Oversight Advisory Board. Also in 2006, the General Assembly codified the advisory group as the Community Integration Advisory Commission (SB 182, 2006) within the exectuive branch to monitor the progress of all executive branch agencies toward community integration of Virginians with disabilities in accordance with all applicable state and federal laws and to make appropriate recommnedations to the Governor (Code of Virginia 2.2-2524). In 2007, Governor Kaine issued Executive Directive 6, which directed state agencies and entities to continue their collaborative efforts to complete the implementation of the Olmstead initiative and to annually complete and update a comprehensive, cross-governmental strategic plan and report to the Governor on the progress of implementation.
Jane Woods served as Secretary of Health and Human Resoures, 2002-2006, during the Warner administration, and Marilyn Tavenner served as Secretatry of Health and Human Resources, 2006-2010, during the Kaine administration.
Scope and Content
The Olmstead Inititative records, 2004-2010, include meeting records of the Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee/Community Integration Advisory Commission, the Community Integration Implementation Team, and joint meetings of both bodies, and document their work to review and cost out the Virginia Olmstead Task Force recommendations and develop a comprehensive cross-governmental strategic plan for community integration. The records were collected and maintained by staff of the Office of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources who attended the meetings. These records include agendas, background documentation, correspondence, meeting records and minutes, notes, plans, presentations, and reports.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Community Integration Implementation Team, 2004-2009.
  - IT meeting, 2004 Jan 27. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - IT meeting, 2004 Jan 27. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - IT meeting, 2004 Feb 25. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - IT meeting, 2004 Mar 24. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - IT meeting, 2004 Apr 27. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - IT meeting, 2004 May 25. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - IT meeting, 2004 June 22. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - IT meeting, 2004 July 27. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - IT meeting, 2004 Aug 24. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - IT meeting, 2004 Sept 24. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - IT meeting, 2004 Oct 26. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - IT meeting, 2004 Dec 21. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - IT meeting, 2005 Jan 26. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - IT meeting, 2005 Feb 23. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - IT meeting, 2005 Apr 26. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - IT meeting, 2005 June 21. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - IT meeting, 2005 Sept 29. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - IT meeting, 2005 Oct 25. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - IT meeting, 2005 Nov 29. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - IT meeting, 2005 Dec 20. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - IT meeting, 2006 Feb 22. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - IT meeting, 2006 Mar 21. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - IT meeting, 2006 Apr 21. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - IT meeting, 2006 May 2. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - IT meeting, 2006 July 11. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - IT meeting, 2006 Aug 22. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - IT meeting, 2006 Oct 17. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - IT meeting, 2006 Dec 19. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - IT meeting, 2007 Mar 20. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - IT meeting, 2007 June 19. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - IT meeting, 2007 Sept 18. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - IT meeting, 2007 Dec 18. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - IT meeting, 2008 Mar 25. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - IT meeting, 2008 June 24. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - IT meeting, 2009 Mar 17. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - IT meeting, 2009 Sept 22. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - IT meeting, 2009 Dec 8. (Box 6)
- Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee, 2004-2010.
  - OAC meeting, 2004 Feb 13. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - OAC meeting, 2004 Apr 14. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - OAC meeting, 2004 May 13. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - OAC meeting, 2004 June 10. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - OAC meeting, 2004 June 18. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - OAC meeting - Cost Out reports, 2004 June 18. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - OAC meeting, 2004 July 1. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - OAC meeting - Cost Out reports, 2004 July 1. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - OAC meeting, 2004 July 22. (Box 8, Folder 5)